Jamie (SG Eco Loop): I'd love to see your smiley faces!
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Hello, everyone! Yes, thanks for waving to me! Otherwise, I felt very lonely.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): ai hi!
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Great to see all of you. For those of you who are here already, thank you for being on time, and some of you are quite early as well. Before we get started, if I could just get you to help me rename your Zoom name to, like, your first name plus your team name.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So that it will be easier for us to identify who you are, that would be super helpful. If any of you have, like, any technical challenges in doing that, you can ping us in the chat as well.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And then I think we still have, like.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): There's some people who are streaming in, so I just wanted to give them maybe one more minute to join before we officially get started.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Alright, so those of you who just came in, please help me rename yourself to include your team name, if you are in a team. If you are solo, just put, like, your first name and your last name, that's also fine.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Then we'll get started very shortly.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay, if you can turn on your cameras, please do so, I'd love to see your smiley faces.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): All right, okay, I think let's get started. We definitely do have people who are still streaming in, I keep hearing the pings in the background, but, we can get started so that we don't make the rest of you wait. So, firstly…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Thank you, and big welcome to the SG Eco Eco Loop 2.0. I know we were really, really very positively, overwhelmed by the number of
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): students, a number of you who are actually interested in building something for Singapore's waste challenges, and have signed up for SG Eco Loop. So today's kickoff is really to welcome you guys, introduce you to why. Why are we looking at waste challenges in Singapore? And hopefully, you know, you'll become very clear as to what the hackathon is about, what are the challenges.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And afterwards, if there are any questions… oh, actually, not afterwards, anytime you have any questions, you can raise your hand if you want to unmute yourself.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): and ask a question, or you can put it into the chat, over here. So I will be monitoring the chat, so if I see your questions coming in anytime.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): I'll find the right time to address the questions that you have.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Alright, so feel free to reach out with any questions over here, and if you don't get a chance to ask your questions, during the session, you can ask me at the end, or you can also reach out to me over email as well as WhatsApp. So I think all of you would have been receiving plenty of emails and communications from me, under the SG Eco Loop at SDTA.org. SG email. So that's me.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Hopefully you guys recognize me from the photo I put, so that I wanted you guys to feel a little bit more familiar with our team.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Alright, so we're gonna get started right now, and the first thing I'd like to do is to introduce Clara Chen, the founder of SDTA, who is the non-profit that has put together this SG Eco Eco Loop Programme. So, Clara, over to you to introduce…
Clara (SG Eco Loop): Thanks, Jamie, for doing the kickoff. Good afternoon, everyone.
Clara (SG Eco Loop): My name is Clara, and I founded the Singapore Detect Alliance because, you know, I believe that the best solutions to our problems, humanity's problems, we won't come from boardrooms alone. For context, before Singapore Detect Alliance was a non-profit organization, it builds companies and invests in these companies and take them to go to market, also to solve societal problems.
Clara (SG Eco Loop): You know, but…
Clara (SG Eco Loop): Over time, I realized the people closest to the problems, who will be able to find amazing solutions, they're typically younger, like yourself, and they're closest to these problems, so they understand the problems enough.
Clara (SG Eco Loop): And so, those with the resources, you know, like those from the boardrooms, the investors, you know, the venture builders, they can provide the tools, the network, and of course, trust for you guys to build.
Clara (SG Eco Loop): Now, of course, this belief is why we converted ourselves into a non-profit, and we work with the Ministry of Sustainability and Environment, SG Co-Fund, and Thomasix Foundation's Oscar Fund.
Clara (SG Eco Loop): to launch the SG Koh Loop Programme last year. And so last year in our pilot cohort, it was really just a testbed. So we worked with about 100 ITE students, from, sorry, IT College East, sorry, College Central, IT College Central.
Clara (SG Eco Loop): Now, the Humber students didn't just learn about plastic waste, they built 25 solutions to tackle these problems, that's plaguing us at home, as a community.
Clara (SG Eco Loop): So, and last year on Showcase Day, the top 5 teams presented their solutions to an audience of about 300.
Clara (SG Eco Loop): So, that's the standard that we have set, and this is what we are holding ourselves to in the next two years, and as SG Group now scales nationwide, open to students 17 and above across Singapore, like yourselves. And so, to all our partners supporting this journey.
Clara (SG Eco Loop): to Rebecca, to Jamie, joining us on this journey for the next two years. I think this only works because, you know, we are backing young people like you, so it's not just ideas on paper.
Clara (SG Eco Loop): And SG Eco Loop today is supported by, continues to be supported by the SG Eco Fund, and catalyzed by, Thomasik Foundation, Oscar, and, you know, SCAPE. We also have supporters from Lenovo, in support of National Youth Council, SGU Plan, Go Green SG, Switch by Enterprise Singapore.
Clara (SG Eco Loop): And officially, our IHL partners, ITE, the three different colleges, SUSS, and a couple of other universities, and of course, a whole host of community partners. Now, I'll let Jamie introduce these community partners to you as we go along the program.
Clara (SG Eco Loop): So, my last word is really to everyone in this room who are starting today.
Clara (SG Eco Loop): We need to go and build something real that we can help you to deploy in an industry you can see working live.
Clara (SG Eco Loop): Let's begin.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Thank you so much, Clara. Hope everyone's excited. Okay, so, big welcome to all of you. You guys are truly the stars of this program. Without you, there will be no SG Ko Loop, so…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): These are a few ground rules, not ground rules, housekeeping matters, so repeating myself for those who just joined, if you can, please rename your Zoom name to your first name, as well as your team name, so if it's me, maybe, like, Jamie, that's right, SG Ko Loop.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): If you can, please keep your cameras on. Do mute your audio unless you are speaking, and if you have any questions, you can raise your hands using the Zoom function, or you can ask the questions in the chat anytime. I will be monitoring the chat.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So I will find the right time to address the questions that you have.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): There are some reminders for you guys. I would love for you, during today, as well as the rest of the program, please remember to be respectful of one another. We are all learning here. And also, while this is actually Eco Loop has a competition element, because there's prizes, which I'll share more about soon, it is also a learning environment.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So please, you know, don't be, don't be too fierce about it, and have some friendly competition, amongst each other, alright?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): With this program, there will be attendance taking for each of the sessions for our tracking, so if you are able to take out your phones and scan this QR code for your attendance
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): You'll also see this for each of the subsequent sessions.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): my colleague Rebecca will help to put the link into the chat now if you have trouble scanning it, so you can also, get the link from the chat itself, in a short while. The other thing is,
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): On communications. So, on communications, there will be two main ways of comms. Number one is over email, so those of you, I mean, for all of you here, you definitely have received by email, sharing the Zoom, sharing the welcome email. We will also have WhatsApp, so
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): This will be a WhatsApp community with one main general channel where you can have conversations about any topic relating to SG Eco Loop or relating to sustainability. There will also be subgroups, which are private, where I will add you as well as your match mentor in that group, so that you can kind of have those conversations within your team relating to SG Eco Loop. So.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): After this, I will be sending you guys, to your WhatsApp, and either I'll directly add you into the group, or… because some of you have privacy permissions on, so I will send
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): you a link directly from, as a direct message. So you'll, you'll see a message from my number, 90195694. Please don't ignore it, it's not a spam.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And the other thing is, I did notice that some of the emails that I've sent have been vows, and have been flagged as spam, so if you could help me add my email to your safe sender list on your email to make sure that you are receiving the emails for all the program matters, please do so.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): If, after this, you've got any questions around comms, around email, feel free to reach out.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): All right.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Without further ado, we'll dive into the objective of the SG Eco Eco Loop Programme. So, the primary objective is really for you guys to build prototypes to divert food waste and plastic waste from our waste systems.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, what can a prototype be? It can be physical, it can be digital, it can be community, initiative.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): It could be a redesigned workflow or system, it could be a Wizard of Oz prototype. And what that means is that it looks automated to the user, but because we are at the prototype level.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): It can be something that is actually done manually behind the scenes.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): You can also come up with things that are, like, an incentive model. So.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): it can really be up to you how it looks like, as long as it's a good representation of what you do want to build. So this is, like, a version 1 of what you want to build.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, as I said, it's a good representation of your proposed solution that you can use to test, you get feedback, and also present at the showcase.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Alright, so, the hackathon challenge and the prices. So, as shared over email, there are two main prizes. The first price is the biggest impact price. This price is decided by the MOSES kg of waste, specifically plastic and or food waste that's diverted from landfill.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And by diverted, it can be you are reducing it, you are repurposing it, you are recycling it. And this, ways that we are diverting does not need to be directly attributed to your prototype.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Do you understand what that means? That means if, say, your prototype is an app.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): for, people to discover where they can, or maybe discover what, items are recyclable and not… what are not recyclable. Your impact can still be created. Say, okay, you are getting your family members to do recycling together with you, you are taking pictures of what you are recycling.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): That also counts, so it can be not related, it can be unrelated, alright? And then the second prize is the best innovation price. So we'll have our mentors, our industry mentors, who will be joining the jury panel, and then at the showcase, they will go around to all your, you know, your booths, where you'll be sharing about your prototype.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): They will grade you on the 5 criteria. On these 5 criteria, all weighted equally. So that's problem understanding, originality, feasibility, potential impact, as well as pitch and clarity.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So after this, I hope all of you, kind of read through this, definitions to see how you want to make… to make sure that whatever you are building fulfill this criteria. So if, you know, you score
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): fairly well on only one thing, and not very well on the other things, then most likely you will lose to a different team that is doing very well on all the above. So try as much as possible to… to see that, make sure your prototype is, you know, is very clear what is the problem you are solving.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): You are doing something that is quite original, it hasn't been done here, maybe it's been done very, you know, in a different country, and how would you adapt that solution to Singapore? It could be thinking about how feasible and realistic it would be to build this, solution.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And what is the potential impact? So how much waste could it be… could it… could your solution possibly divert when, you know, it's, deployed at skill? Are you explaining your problem, your solution, and your results clearly? So all of these things will…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): lead to our final winners, alright, for the biggest impact, as well as the best innovation.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Alright, so with this competition, there are some deliverables that you will have to submit ahead of the kickoff, sorry, ahead of the showcase. So, the showcase is on the 2nd of October, so the most important thing is you need to have your prototype.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So this is the… like I was sharing earlier, it can be a physical prototype, it can be a digital one, it can be a combination, that is solving a plastic or waste problem. You can get creative with how you display your prototype. Are you doing a poster board? Do you have a video that's looping on a laptop? Do you have photos that you are printing, or you are showcasing on your slides?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And, etc. And then,
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): that prototype, as well as the explanation, because the mentors, they are not just gonna look at the prototype, they are gonna talk to you, they are gonna ask you, so what have you built? Tell me about what you've built, why you've built it, and you have to kind of be able to present what
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): It's the prototype that you've built, why you're building it, and that will fall into the scoring that the judges will be doing.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): The second deliverable is a scale-up plan. So, this will be in a Slack format, which I'll share in more detail towards the end, where you are sharing what are the learnings that you have made from
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): building a prototype, how would you plan to scale or pivot, if you were to continue building this?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And the next deliverable is a trash diary. So this is the trash di… this trash diary will be used to assess, which team is the team that makes the biggest impact, and that would be the winner for the price. So try and lock your, progress every week.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Aim for 20 kg or more per team.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, that you can win. So, along the way, we will actually announce in the WhatsApp group, okay, who is maybe the leading team, or which team has the highest amount right now, so that you can have a sense as to how the other teams are doing. And then, you can see if you need to recycle more, or divert more waste.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And the fourth deliverable is a people lock.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, we want, sustainability to be something that not just you are aware of, but also the people around you. So that could be your family, your friends, your neighbors, maybe the people in your community. So you should be logging all the individuals that you engage during, this journey, whether you are sharing with them about SG Eco Eco Loop sharing about, your recycling campaign with them.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): You are engaging them to do your surveys, or engaging them to be your test users.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Log it down. So all of this will have, templates for you, not all of it, sorry. The Trash Diaries, the people log will have templates for you, which I'll share after this in a follow-up email, where I'll also be sharing the slides. I'll also be sharing the recording of today's session, so if needed, you can go back and watch it.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Alright. Okay.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, I have a question, Oren. How do you, prevent… how would I… how would we prevent people from cheating? I love that question. So…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): The… the way we are, kind of…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Monitoring your waste is,
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): we really, really hope that you will be… you will use integrity, all of you will be integrity, for how you are creating the waste, or how you are tracking your waste. We really don't want to see teams that, are actually
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): purposefully creating more ways so that you can show that you're recycling them, that is really not the intention. And if you really do that just to win this competition, then I would say, you know, maybe, our education system, the way we have been communicating our program is not helpful. So, actually, what I want to emphasize is beyond the prizes, I really, really hope that the bigger takeaway
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): all of you will have from the SG Eco Eco Loop Programme is actually
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): the learnings that you will take from here beyond the prices. So it's the learnings of what are the sustainability challenges that Singapore faces.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): What are the innovation processes? What are the innovation frameworks? Who are the people in this ecosystem who can actually, help you in building a career in sustainability?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Alright, so hopefully that addresses, that we will require you guys to put in, photos, of all the trash that you are diverting as well.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay, prototyping budget. So, we have managed to get, kind of support from our funding partners, like SG Eco Fund, as well as Thomasic Foundation, to, put together a budget for you guys to prepare your prototype. So, that is $200 per prototype.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, every team, you can actually do more than one prototype each, but you, of course, you must complete it and showcase it.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Provided that the concepts are different. So…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): That is not something I will necessarily go into detail right now, but if your team is interested to unlocking this second budget for the second prototype, and you want to just clarify if your… you have to clarify if your concepts are distinct first.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Just reach out to us, let us know what are the two things, or even three prototypes that you are thinking of. We'll let you know if they are eligible for the second $200 budget.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Alright, so in terms of, expenses that you can spend this $200 budget on, we have a short white list.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So you can, when you get the slides, you can click for the full list, but there will be things like your stationery, your craft materials, it can… it does include AI, tools like claud, Gemini, ChatGPT, includes, design tools like Canva, tools for 3D design, 3D design and modeling, as well as 3D printing.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, beyond this list, you have to write to us to tell us what is it that you want to purchase, what's it for, how it relates to your prototype, and how much it will cost, and get our approval before you spend it. Otherwise, you may not get reimbursed.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And then, yeah, so that's for non-whitelisted expenses. And what is the claims process? There is a form for this. Fill it out,
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Use it as, fill it out as a Google Sheet, tag us when you are done.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And… you will receive your PayNow transfer within 1 to 3 business days, if all the documentations are complete.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Right, so we are allowing for you guys to, apply for this in two manners. One is after you have purchased, and then you send us the invoice.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): and as well as this template. The other is actually an advance transfer. So that means, ahead of you spending the money, you fill out this form, you give us kind of the requested documents, and we can transfer you that money before you buy.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Alright, so if anything's unclear on the reimbursement process, again, ask us anytime.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So right now, I have something for you guys, which is hopefully going to be a little bit interesting, which is a Kahoot.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Chris, I am going to flash up the Koh Hood screen right now, so bring out your phones and devices so that you can, scan the QR code.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Let's give it a second.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Alright!
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Awesome, I can see you guys joining.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Maybe 10 more seconds, unless you need more time.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Alright, I will get started.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Bice!
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): 4… Wee.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Too!
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And… Wan.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay, I… because you… there's still a lot of yu coming in, I'm gonna just give it a shot while more.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Yeah, I can see that you guys are excited.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay, we have 70 people, who have joined. Okay, we're just gonna get started, okay?
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And then those.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): of you who are a little bit slow, hopefully you can still join as we go.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, let's go!
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Alright, we're gonna start out…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): First question, roughly how much waste does the average person in a Singapore household throw out per day? 0.3 kg, 0.8 kg, 2KG, or 5?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Alright, the answer is 0.8 kg, and 18 of you got that right. Awesome.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, that was, the amount of daily domestic waste generated per capita in 2025, 0.83 kgs. Oh, Elo, Marcus, Chloe, Doria, and JX. Awesome. Next question, true or false?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Singapore recycles more than 1 in 5, which is roughly 20% of plastic items that are thrown away. Is it true or false?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Alright, the answer is actually false! So, in 2025, we actually generated
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): 890 tons of plastic waste, and recycled just 34,000 tons. So actually, it's only 4%, nowhere close to 20%.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Alright, so we have Marcus now on top.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And then the next question, what percentage of simple domestic recycling actually gets recycled?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So what's the overall recycling rate? Is it 11%?
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): It's at 32%.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Is it 53%, or is it 74%?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): 11% and 38 of you got that right. That's majority. That's well done. Johan, very good.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay, next, is which of these can actually go into Singapore's blue recycling bin?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): A used cardboard pizza box, all receipts, rinsed and dried metal cans, or clean styrofoam box.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): The answer is rinse and dried metal cans. Yay, very good, all of you, okay, not all, but most of you did get this correct, which is great. So, things like your pizza boxes, you can't recycle them, even though they are cardboard, because they would be dirty already. All receipts, even though they are paper-based.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Actually, a lot of the receipts are, say, thermal paper, where there is a chemical coating, so they're actually not recyclable. And styrofoam boxes are also not recyclable.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And then, let's see, on the scoreboard, yes, we still have, Johan in the first place.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Next question. What is buried at Pula Sumakao, Singapore's only landfill? Is it household rubbish, waste from neighboring countries, construction debris and treated sludge, or recycling that is rejected at a recycling plant?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): The answer is construction, debris, and treated sludge. So, actually, most… okay, waste from neighboring countries is definitely wrong. We don't take any waste from neighboring countries.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): For things like household rubbish or recycling that is rejected at the recycling punt, actually all of that goes into our incinerators first, and only when it's in, like, the
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): but insulation.
Alan: Ed? Interesting.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): that is, what ends up on Pulau's markup, right? So, yeah.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): surprising, right, for many of you. So only construction, debris, and treated sludge go directly to the lead field.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay, next question! Oh, Chloe, well done! Next one is, when is Pulao's Macau landfill projected to be full at current rates? Is it 2035? 2050, 2080, or never?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Most of you got that right again, so it's 2035 indeed. So that's actually in less than 10 years' time, that's about 9 years away. So what are we gonna do when our landfill is fully filled?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): You know, that's why there are conversations about using the other islands and so on, so, you know, as much as possible, let's try and delay when these landfills will fill up, okay?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Then, next… oh, let's see the scoreboard. Chloe's still at the top, but we have had some of movements, so we can still catch up.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Next question. Let's say a cafe uses compostable cutlery. If you toss the cutlery into a home compost bin, what most likely happens?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Answer is, it stays mostly intact for months, possibly over a year. So why is that the case? Is there is a big difference between home composting and industrial composting.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, when items are marketed as compostable, so like, you know, you buy a compostable paper plates and so on from the supermarket, they are actually mostly only compostable in industrial conditions where there's higher heat, there's controlled moisture, and so on. So, it's actually a lot of marketing going on.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): When terms like this are used without the consumers really understanding Understanding what they need.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So… oh, wait, and don't cry, okay? So, Joanne, Johan, sorry, still, first place.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Let's go! Next question!
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Which describes material that can be broken down by microorganisms, bacteria, and fungi into natural elements over time.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): The answer is biodegradable, which most of you got that right as well. So, biodegradable is actually something that can be used as a greenwashing marketing term sometimes.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Because there's no required time frame, there's no required set of conditions, so it doesn't promise how fast or how completely something actually breaks down. So over time could be, like, over 100 years, could be over 10 years, it could be over 1 year. So that makes a difference, but
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): People don't necessarily know about that, okay? So…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): I think we are on to our final, final question.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Which… oh, and let's see, we are…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Johan is still in the first place! Well done! Whether there'll be an overthrowing of the first place leader, we'll find out after this last question. So for this final question, what is a prototype?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Is it a business plan describing the concept and how you plan to build it? Is it a demo product that's ready to sell to one customer, or is it a physical model made of cardboard or 3D printed parts?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Or is it a rough, testable version of an idea? So if you listen carefully to what I introduced right at the start, you should be able to get this.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): That's right, it is a rough, testable version of an idea. So, a physical model can be a prototype, but not all prototypes have to be a physical model. A business plan is just a business plan.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): You don't have anything physical, or you don't have anything visual to show. So the important point of a prototype is that it's testable.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): testable, so you can get results, you can get feedback, so you know what to build for your next version. Okay? So, let's see if Johan is still in first place, or we have. In third place, Chloe! Congratulations!
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Second place, we have Chongyu. And in first place, we have…
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): RIHAN!
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Alright, well done, everybody! I hope you guys have learned something from this. And Kylie and Sharis in 4th and 5th.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Well done!
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): I'm gonna just, like, take a screenshot of this if,
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): You know, so that we can save this as a memory.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Alright, very good.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, now that, we have finished the queue.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Koh, let me go back to the slides.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So I hope you guys have learned a little bit about waste problems, but there's so much more to know, and this is hopefully just something to, like, pique your interest, and later on you can go and read more about it.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So the next thing is, like, okay, we have the problem, we have so many different waste challenges, so how can we tackle waste?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Alright? So… Short of hands, who has heard this before? Reduce, reuse, recycle.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): The Trios… Show of hands.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Yeah?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): People have heard of this? Okay.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Yes, very familiar.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Did you know there are actually 6 other R's?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): They are very, very closely related to race reduction. They actually are also very important. So hopefully after this, you'll be able to learn more RS. You don't have to remember all of them, it won't be tested in the exam, but hopefully you can use some of these RS in your… in building the prototype.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Alright, so let's go and… let's start, right, and see what are the 9 R's.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So the most… actually, one of the most valuable R is the first R, which is refuse.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So if you just refuse it, At that point.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): you don't even create the waste, right? There's no recycling, there's no reduction to talk about, it's just, we just say no. So that's, like, if you bring your own bag to the supermarket, or you bring your own, like, container box to the food stall, to tapao, instead of taking their plastic containers, these are all ways to refuse.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Another R is to rethink.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, rethinking the model.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): so that less is wasted. So, an example is the Three Dots, marketplace, which is a marketplace where suppliers' unsold or imperfect stock can be listed, that can be sold to other people instead of their regular customers, so that
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): It can still be used by somebody before it expires or it spoils.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): The third R, which we are familiar with, is reducing. So I want to give an example of Lumitix, which is a startup that has a smart BIN, which is used in restaurants, to track, you know, what are the food that's thrown away. So they have a smart camera, they can use the visual intelligence to identify what's being thrown away on a daily basis, so that there's data, so that next time the kitchen will be like, oh, my
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Chak koio always get thrown away, so I cook less chakotiao next time.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Alright?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Then, when you raise your hand, would you like to ask a question?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Oh, okay, sorry, that was from my question just now, is it? Whether you have heard of that tree asked? Alright,
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): The next are, reuse. So we have Muse, which I won't talk about, because in a short while, we'll actually have the CEO of Muse come and share about their journey at Muse.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, I'll let him share with you what they do. For repair, you know, that's another R, where some of you may have heard of Repair Kopitiam. So, they're actually an initiative where volunteers, who are coaches.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Teach people how to,
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): repair and mend broken electronics or appliances. So, you can, like, if your fence spoiled, most people are just like, okay, my fence spoiled, I'm gonna throw it away, I'm gonna buy a new one.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): But if we learn to repair, maybe we can diagnose why it's spoiled, or maybe it's just the button that's broken, maybe I replace this button, and it will work again. So all I need to do is to get a new part, replace it, repair it, and then I can use it again, and this thing can use for another 5 years. So that's another R.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Refurbish is to restore an old product to working order. So, I think a lot of you will have heard, like, you know, you buy a refurbished mobile phone or a refurbished laptop. Basically, you just see what's wrong with it, you can upgrade certain parts or replace certain parts.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And then, it can be used again. So, a company like Engineering Goods is actually a charity that refurbishes used laptops and computers and passes them to low-income families and students, so that all these electronics are also not kept in the e-waste strip.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Alright.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And next up, we have, give me a second…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Next up, we have, repurposed.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): That means to turn something, turn something existing into something with a new use. So, for example, the interchange is a circular economy lab that turns everyday waste into new products that they can sell.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, for example, you know, when you go to NDP, you have this, like, I don't know what they're called, the plastic
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): things that make noise. Afterwards, it's thrown away. There's a lot of plastic that's always thrown away every year. So this setup actually are clappers! Thank you, Kaen! So they are called clappers, and then what they did is they cut it up, and they actually sewed it into tote bags.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So that this material continues to be used. Tundel sticks, great.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Then, the next thing is recycle, which you guys are very familiar with, probably. Yes, oh, by the way, if you guys need to take a break anytime, buy a break or anything, just go and come back, you don't have to… you don't have to ask for permission.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Then for, Megorium. So, Megorium is actually a Singapore company.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): You know, when we think about recycling plastic, we think that plastic recycled can be used to make other plastics. But actually, what they did is they made it into bitumen, new bitumen, which is a road paving material that is actually able to withstand the weight of your cars, to withstand all the weather conditions, and use on our roads, including at TWAS.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And finally, the last R is recover, which is to get energy or material from what's left. So, you know, after we've tried to reuse it, we've tried to repurpose it.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And there's nothing else that we can do with that material. We burn it.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): To get energy from it. So, in Singapore, we have the TWAS Nexus, which is our upcoming integrated waste and water facility, where incinerable waste, are actually converted into biogas and electricity.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And then part of it is to power the plant itself, and part of it can power the, maybe the users in the vicinity.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): All right.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, let's take a quick pause here.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Thanks.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): If we have… Founder of Muse… Here, with us.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): I think he's not joined yet. So, we'll skip this for now, and come back to this when, Jonathan joins us.
Alexia: Shit. How's this? Oh, shit, hey guys.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Bye! Alright, we'll come back to this in a short while. So…
Jasmine: Pass it to us tomorrow.
Jasmine: Hannah.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Sorry. I think what we'll do is… let's take a short break here. Let's take a 5-minute break. For those of you who might need a bio break, we'll take a short 5-minute break here, and the next thing that we are going to talk about is the Diable Diamond innovation process.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Or innovation framework. And in the meantime, for those of you who have just, who just… who came in after the start and missed out on these, links, and so on, please help me with taking your attendance.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): help me join the WhatsApp community as well. Then, I'll be here if any of you have any questions. So we'll do a 5 minutes break, come back at 3.40,
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): 7.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Singapore time. I assume all of you are in Singapore right now. So, come back at 3.47, okay?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Hi, Jonathan!
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Thanks for dialing in!
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): Hi.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Thank you so much. So, we are just taking a short break. The students will be back at 3.47 in 2 minutes' time, and then I'll get you to share about music.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): Sounds good.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Thank you so much.
Alan: Okay, sorry,
Alan: It's a trike, not…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Alright, is everyone back? If you are back and possible, do turn on your cameras.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Thank you, Kaen.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Alright.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Just now we were talking about the 9Rs, and then I skipped one of the R's so that, Jonathan, the CEO of Meals, can share with us, about what his company does. So, allow me to welcome Jonathan Tostevin, CEO of Mules.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Over to you, Jonathan.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): Hey! Hey, everyone.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): Nice to meet you all, thank you for your time today. Jamie, do you want to tell me to talk to my slide, or just… do you want me to just talk to, kind of, more just, the story that… of our… of our company?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Please do the story.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): Sure, sure. Cool. So, I mean, first of all, MUSE stands for multiple use, if that wasn't clear, to any of you from before.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): It really comes out of a desire to try and tackle, the issues of single-use waste, and particularly single-use plastic waste and single-use packaging waste. Takeaway packaging, food, drink, takeaway packaging that we use all the time.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): Like, for me and for the other part… members of the team who kind of started the company with me, this was around 2018, 2019, when, like, ocean plastic waste was a really big topic, lots of documentaries and news about it, and…
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): it was, like, something that was very clear, something that was very clear, but, like, hidden came very clear. So, like, all this stuff we see around us, we suddenly thought, you know, where does this go? What happens to it? You know, what is actually… and the sheer scale of the problem. So, like, we kind of… I think all amongst us all individually had journeys where we were…
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): you know, just overwhelmed by the number of items that we consume globally, just in terms of kind of packaging. And, you know, just the billions, billions of items. The tiny amounts of time that we use them for, like 5 or 10 minutes max, you know, if you think about how long you get your coffee or your food for, and where it goes when it's done, you know. In Singapore, most of that waste is collected and incinerated.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): And that is, like, the best case scenario. The best case scenario is basically we burn it all.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): And then we stick it in landfill. And it just feels like a really… felt to me like a really ineffective solution, and that's to say, that's the best case scenario. In many other countries, it's either shipped off, to other parts of the world, where it's managed ineffectively.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): beautiful, it goes into rivers, goes into the ocean, destroys habitats, ends up in our food cycle. You know, there's a whole range of harmful impacts of this. And also a significant carbon emission impact from producing all this packaging, you know, billions and billions and billions of these items every year.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): a significant amount of the plastic produced is for packaging and for food and drink packaging. There's one estimate that it… that kind of the carbon emissions associated with food and drink packaging is around, like, 1% of the total carbon emissions, of the total global carbon budget, which is insane when you think about what we actually use it for. So, for me, personally, I feel just, like, that we could do a lot better. You know, so many other parts of our
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): Economy and our culture, you know, we've… we've improved, we've made better, we've made smarter, and it just feels like this is a very wasteful, ineffective…
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): subpar way of living, of way of being, and I just think there should be a better way to do it. That's kind of really my motivation for getting into this space and doing something about it,
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): when, we then started looking at what to do about it, and, you know, some existing solutions, you know, have existed for a while, so, you know, recycling, we have compostable packaging, but there are both issues with both of those. Like, recycling, as I'm sure most of you will be aware if you're on this call, is,
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): can be effective in very specific circumstances with, like, very good resource recovery, but I would say, like, public recycling generally is low outside of aluminium
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): and to some extent, cardboard. You know, for takeaway packaging items, they're very, very difficult to recycle. They're lightweight, they're often spoiled with food. It's very difficult to turn those items back into something of value. And also, the economics just don't make any sense. So, these things don't get recycled.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): Compostable packaging can work in some instances again, but it needs… often needs, the right infrastructure around it, to collect back and, again, do something effective with it, or if it's properly compostable and properly biodegradable, and then it kind of will dissolve in the seas, then it's not going to hold your drink very well, you know? So, like.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): It's kind of obvious, really. So, there's, like, an obvious gap there. There's not really a solution that was fixing the problem.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): And reuse is an idea that's obviously been around for a long time. People used to reuse, food and drink packaging all the time, you know, kind of the milkman model, or, even in Singapore from the 60s, you know, people getting… I forget the name, that escaped me, but, like, from your copy in, like, a… in, like, an aluminium tin.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): And people would just reuse this stuff all the time. So it's something that our grandparents used to do without really thinking about it, because there wasn't this kind of great influx of cheap plastic packaging.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): And so, we thought, well, if there's a way to make reuse… bring reuse back, but make it more convenient, and whether we could use tech to enable that. So that's kind of really how we started, and this, how do we make it simple and convenient has kind of really been at the heart of everything we've tried to do since then.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): We, I guess, initially tried to just bring reuse to market, but realized that basically everyone… single use is so, so simple, so easy, so convenient, so cheap.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): that there isn't really enough of an incentive for people to try a different option, unless you get to regulations and taxes and laws, but they only come in when there's a suitable system in place that people are willing to move to. So you can't really rely on that. You've got to try and find… bring something else to market in a different way, and then eventually regulation will come in, but…
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): So we've… we… our focus and our mission now is really to make reuse as simple as possible, to make it the norm, to make it second nature. And that's what our company has done. So,
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): like, what we do now, and what we do as a company, is we provide, reusable packaging systems and solutions, to B2B clients, across the world. We provide reusable packaging, so, like, reusable cups, food containers, basically anything, really, that's reusable. The logistics and washing, so
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): kind of cycle those back through, so we will collect, and we will wash, sanitize, and put that back into circulation. We'll either do that ourselves or through third parties, and underneath that all, we have a tracking data platform that tracks every individual item in our system. So every item has a unique serialized code, whether that's a QR or an RFID tag, that allows us to track it through our solution, so we can know whether it's with a vendor.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): A consumer, a return point, our washing station.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): We know, we're able to turn that into, you know, better inventory management, for ourselves and for our clients, impact reporting, again, for our clients, and also build on top of that base tracking platform with.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): behavioral tools that, incentivize or penalize… incentivize return or penalize loss. So basically ensure that items come back more quickly.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): more correctly, more robustly, and back into our solution, so that reusable items actually get returned and reused over and over again. Because obviously, if they're not reused, then it's obviously not an effective solution.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): From either a sustainability or a commercial point of view.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): I'll pause in a minute, but, like, I guess in terms of where we focus now, we've gone on a long journey, and I can cover some of that if it's interesting, but where we focus now really is around large-scale,
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): closed, ideally closed, locations, so we look at stadiums, large-scale events, workplaces, schools, universities, tourist environments, where we get a large enough volume to make the commercials work for doing the whole reverse logistics, and we're able to control some of the way that people
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): behave and interact.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): ultimately, we'll be able to do this at city level, but city level's a big undertaking for startup, and for where we are in the, kind of, journey towards regulation. So we're kind of effectively creating, like, mini-cities with,
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): And also it's easier to not work with government, because you have a whole set of, like, public, procurement rules and, laws and stuff you have to, would need to be changed, so you can work… we work with, like, private, landlords,
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): developers, even if they're associated with government, that's fine, but just people who are able to help us change the way that things work more easily within their environment. So, some of the more recent, programs we've run in Singapore are…
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): We launched earlier this year a vending machine program with Income Insurance in their offices, so their staff can basically, get a reasonable container when they're heading out to get their lunch, to tap out, and then drop it back into a smart return BIN when they're done.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): We empty that, wash it, and cycle it back through for them. They get data on their impact, their staff also get rewards when they return, or entered into a lottery when they return, and that's something we kind of run for income.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): We're also doing something with WWF in Raffles City area, again, a kind of…
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): Which is linked to the income program I mentioned, and that's kind of more around how do we build, can we reward… how effectively can we use rewards to incentivize return, and kind of removing some of the friction around the user experience, but…
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): I'll just pause there. I don't know if you want to open up for questions, Jamie, or if you want me to stop, or cover any other areas that I'm happy to.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Thank you. I would love for the students, any of you, if you have any questions for Jonathan, if you want to unmute and ask, or if you're a bit shy and you want to send it in the chat.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): please go ahead. I do have one question for you, Jonathan, which is, you know, these students, are actually going to try and build a prototype in 6 weeks' time to tackle plastic waste or food waste challenges. What would be some of the advice you would give them
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): To building that prototype.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): Oh, man. Okay, so I'd say the… you're gonna get it wrong. The first thing you come up with will be wrong, the second thing you'll come up will be wrong, the third thing you come up with will be wrong. Basically, whatever you come up with will be wrong. It'll just be maybe less wrong each time.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): And the important thing is to just get out there, test it, get feedback. Definitely, you know, getting real user feedback, and as much as possible, making that a real experiential feedback, so you're not just, like… you're not just asking people what they think, because they'll tell you what you think you want to hear, but actually getting them to do something that is testing what you're…
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): your prototyping, and then expecting that you're going to be wrong, basically. And then, you know, maybe you're 50% right first time, and then you get it 60%, 70%, 80%. We're still not, you know, 100% right with what we're doing, and we're still testing and learning all the time. So it's basically an ongoing journey.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Thank you so much, Jonathan. In the chat, we have a question from Jayen.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): He, he or she asked which part of the business, is it hardware, washing, or logistics, or data collection, etc, brings the most challenges in terms of cost or feasibility.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): The cost bit is the washing logistics,
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): You know, we're effectively, you know, single-use
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): prices don't include the cost of collecting single-use and disposing of it. So we're effectively adding
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): We're having to, you know, add in another couple of cost-line items that single-use packaging providers don't have to consider. So we're always trying to, you know, try and get that as low as possible, and that's really the… the logistics of collecting these items.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): You know, unless we're doing serious scale, like, unless we're doing a stadium, is always gonna… is always, one of the biggest barriers to,
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): To getting reuse systems up and running.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): At the cost, I think, like, the feasibility really is,
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): Just making it as simple as possible for people to use, and… but creating the right environment for them to return it, and that's kind of the kind of the knack, and every environment is slightly different, and you kind of need to design it differently to recognize that.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Thank you.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Thanks, Jonathan. Did any other people have questions for Jonathan?
Marcus (ricecakes): Yeah, hi.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Otherwise, we will… go ahead, Marcus.
Marcus (ricecakes): Yeah, so, I wanted to ask you, right, is this model actually economically viable? Because, you know, I don't see any real,
Marcus (ricecakes): profit that you can generate from this. So, in the first place, what's your profit model, you know? Are you non-profit, or are you for-profit? And if you are for-profit, how do you manage to make it viable?
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): Yeah, very good question. And I see Elvis's as well, which is also a very good question, I'll come on to.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): So, we're a for-profit company, we're not yet profitable, so we're still reliant on, an investment from
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): investors, I guess, to kind of grow… to grow the business. We are reaching that, and should be there towards the end of next year. They're obviously gross profitable, like, you know, gross margin profitable, but not… not kind of, net margin.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): We are not as cheap as single use.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): In most cases. So… which is obviously a challenge to scale, and eventually… there are eventually a few things will happen. One is that we'll be a large enough scale to be able to bring that price down to compete. Secondly, the single use will be taxed or banned, or effectively
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): costed in some way that brings its level up to us. Like, you already see it with extended producer responsibility. You know, those are basically costs on bringing in single-use packaging into the country, and so that effectively adds on a cost to having single-use packaging, so even though you're paying, like, I don't know, 5, 10 cents for a
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): for a plastic cup, you're then playing something on top of that. That's still quite a small amount, but eventually that will… that will grow. So those two things will converge, and that scale point for us is also key. I mean, we're a small company, we're trying to compete with
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): you know, SKP, which produced, like, billions of items a year, and so you're able to do that as some serious,
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): serious, costs. So what we need to do… so what we… I guess what we're doing, how do we even sell anything, is we're…
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): well, I guess the market, to some degree, wants to move away from single-use packaging, and that may be because they see value in it for their stakeholders, so, like, a corporate might decide that it doesn't want to have cheap single-use packaging, it wants to show that it's being environmentally friendly.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): E, you know, a stadium might decide that,
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): yeah, it's kind of, again, CSR reasons or marketing value, so there are some, the data from this stuff is quite important and quite valuable. They can brand these items as well, so again, a bit like good branding value. So there's… there are… there are ways we play around the margin, other than the fact that people just would like to shift away from using single-use packaging, and want to… ultimately, it's, I guess, a marketing or a internal or external marketing story that they want…
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): They want to be able to tell.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): That's not to say we're not close in cost on some. Like, say for stadiums, we are not far off cost of single use, and so, you know, that jump that they're making to using us isn't as big as, say, I know, a smaller scale provider, where my cost would be a lot higher.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): Oh, sorry, and Elvis's question.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): I mean, how long do I have? I probably… I'd probably be where I am now. I, you know, the journey would have just, like, shortcuted that journey significantly. You know, we started off, like, with a B2C solution, like an app that users would…
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): and I used a subscription model, like, it was free for businesses, and we were building a network of cafes that users could borrow and return from. I would probably not bother… I definitely wouldn't have done that again. Like, that was a way towards where we are now, and a way for learning and understanding, but, you know, what we've realized is that it's…
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): is that we're a logistics play, really, an infrastructure provider, and in order to have… make it work, you need to have scale. In order for scale, it needs to be easy. It's not something that people can… we need to have…
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): People choose to use, it's got to be something that's default.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): And so…
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): Yeah, I probably would be… I don't know, I'd have to think about that a bit more to give you something more profound, but essentially, I kind of just have shortcuted our journey to where we are today, and maybe got rid of some of the legacy stuff that we kind of inevitably have now because of the journey we've been on.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Thank you so much, Jonathan. I think hopefully that gives the students a bit of an insight into, you know, if you could start from something and build it into a proper company. This is kind of the up and down journey that you will go through to learn, and I think that
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): when you were initially sharing, some of the things that I caught are some of the, kind of, considerations out there for the students to actually bring with you when you are doing your ideation or your prototyping. So things like incentives, things like economics.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): things like making it simple. These were all things that Jonathan mentioned, you know, in his journey of building mules.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): These were things that were important to figure out. So, when you are trying to implement sustainability solutions, you do have to think about all these things. So, you know, we'll dive a little bit more into those slightly later. But for now, thank you so much, Jonathan. We'd love to take a group photo with you, along with everybody before you jump off.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): All of you, please, if you haven't turned on your cameras, even though I've asked many times, this is the time to turn your camera on, so that we can make sure, you know, your lovely faces are captured, for prosperity.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Alright.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And then,
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Rebecca, are you able to help me with, the photo, or I can do it otherwise?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Hi everyone, there's still, like, a bunch of you who have not turned on your cameras, so please help me to turn that on, otherwise we'll be…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Doing this for the rest of the day.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Alright, very good. Okay, I'm gonna take a picture of the first page now.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, as much as possible, if you are able to, do turn it on, otherwise we understand if you have challenges. Okay, everybody smile, okay?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And then 3, 2, 1, smile with, like, thumbs up or anything, and then I'm gonna just take a screenshot. I have to take multiple, because there's, like, a few of you.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And more…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Right, okay, I think for those of you who have the cameras on, I should have captured you. Thank you so much, everyone. And can we all, like, kind of give a round of applause to Jonathan for coming on, taking time away from his pistols to come and share with you guys his experiences
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Thank you.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): Yeah, pleasure to be with you, and I look forward to meeting my team
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): In a week or two, I guess.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Yes, that's right. Jonathan will actually be one of our mentors, so if any of you, you know, want to, like, book Jonathan to be your mentor, just let me know.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): Russia.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Alright, thank you, Glenda, we'll see you.
Jonathan Tostevin (Observer): game.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Alright, so hopefully… okay, for those of you who turn your cameras on, if you can keep them on, I would appreciate that. If not, I won't… I won't be too picky. Thank you to those who do keep your cameras on and smile at me. That gives me a good sense as to, am I going too fast or anything? If I'm going too fast, you can let me know in the chat as well.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): I do have a tendency to, talk too much and too quickly, so you can tell me to slow down if you need to.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): All right, oh no, escher, I hope your phone's okay. If…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): For any technical issues you guys, accidentally, cut off, don't worry, we have the recording, so you will get a copy of that in case you need to watch afterwards, okay? So, let's move on to the Double Diamond.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay, moving on to the double diamond. So, what is a double diamond? It's something that I'm gonna go through.
Tris: To help guide.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): research of the problem, as well as the design of the solution. So it always goes together. Whenever we are talking about startups, or we are talking about new technologies, or new innovation, actually the first step is not the tech, right? It's not the solution. The first step is actually always
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): the problem. You need to have a meaningful problem that exists, For you to build something, to solve.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Right? So, that's why the problem always starts first. So, I'll start on the left side, which is the problem.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Sorry, Rob.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): I… oops.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay, click this… Yeah.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Hey, what's going on?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Alright, so problem. When you are finding a problem to tackle, you need to take time to understand what is the problem, really, what is the challenge, as well as what is the context of this challenge.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): how do you do that? So you go white first. That's why it's called double diamond, because you're gonna… you're gonna see that when I finish this, kind of framework, it will look like double diamond. So first, you go broad.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, this is you discovering the problem. So, maybe you have certain assumptions about a problem.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): you need to go and research, you know, that… what is really the problem. And when it comes to research, there are a few ways, right, you can do your desktop research. Last time, we used Google. Even last time we used, like, an encyclopedia.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): But nowadays, we use AI, right? A lot of us use AI. I want to remind you, when you are using AI to do your research, please verify the sources.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Because sometimes AI, they reference other AI sources, and then it's all, like, rubbish, you know, the statistics are wrong, the problems are wrong, so you need to make sure that you are validating your sources if you do use AI for your research.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): The other way to do research is, of course.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): talking to people. So we'll share a little bit more on, like, when you are talking to people, people who actually face the problems.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): What would be some tips, to be able to get the information that you need? So, go broad. So, you may have certain assumptions, but make sure you don't focus too much on the assumptions. Go into discovery mode, you know, Torah the Explorer. You are trying to explore what is really the problem, what are the reasons, maybe there are many different things, maybe different people.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Faced that problem differently, you know, so what would be all the insights?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): then you have now gone so wide that, oh, there are too many things for you to do, right? That, you know, there are so many problems in the world, what are you gonna do? Is you now need to kind of choose. So you need to choose the right problem to solve. So maybe you do a survey, 10 people tell you, I have this problem, and then one person tells you, I have this other problem.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Would you solve the problem for the 10 people, or for the 1 person?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So you will choose the… you will probably choose the problem that exists for more people, or you choose the problem that is bigger. You don't choose a problem that, you know, only, like, two people have. You choose a problem that's like, oh, it's actually faced by millions of people, or, you know, everybody will face it on a regular basis. You choose problems that are meaningful.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And then… When you are very clear what is the problem you want to tackle.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Some important questions would be to say, what is the problem?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): who faces this problem? So, if you are very generic and very vague, then that's not a good sign, because when… before you move into solution, if you cannot be very clear who you are targeting, what is the problem you are targeting.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): You know, that's your foundation, right? That means your foundation's not strong, then whatever you put on top, maybe it's totally wrong. So you need to know what are the challenges, what is the context, that we have, okay?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): First diamond is more on the problem. Second diamond, so we are starting to go into the second diamond, which is the solution. So when you are first starting to think about solutions for a problem.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Focus on being creative.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Think outside the box.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Come up with anything and everything, write them all down.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): sometimes at the back of your head, you'll be like, yeah, this one is not possible, this one's not feasible, this one's too difficult. You have all of these things in your head.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): When you're ideating, that's not the right time to think about the limitations.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Put aside the limitations, and just be creative.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): right now. You can also research, you know, what other people are doing, you can sometimes see, maybe some solutions that are in a different industry, maybe not in sustainability, that they have done that's very interesting. Can I apply to, this problem that I'm trying to solve? So be creative.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Then, you have now also gone very wide, and you had to choose what you actually build. Because you cannot build all of this. You have, like, 10 ideas, doesn't mean you can build a prototype for 10 ideas, too many.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, prioritizing. So that's when you put in a little bit more thinking into, okay, for this idea.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): How will I implement it?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Is it feasible at all?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Can it scale? And can it give me a big impact? Can I say, oh, like, maybe this idea can only help me divert 10 kg of waste a year? That's very, very little. Versus this other idea that I think can divert away 100KG of waste a year.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): That's a lot more, right, than the other one. So then you can use that to, prioritize
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): One to two ideas.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): At the end, to…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): actually start building. And that's when you are doing that step of, like, building, you are testing. So a lot of times, maybe for hackathons, right, where it's only just building.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): You only build… you don't really test it, because maybe it's short time, but ours is a 6 weeks program. We've designed some time for you to actually test, which means getting feedback.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So you actually should have something that you are asking maybe your friends to see, okay, this is the app I built, can you give me feedback, like, honest feedback, or maybe, you have, kind of a prototype that you are using to divert waste in your school canteen, maybe for at least one day. What is the finding of that?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay? So, once again, when you are building and testing the solution, you are addressing very clearly the…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): What you are building?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Who you are building it for, so who will be the users of this thing that you are building?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): why is your solution going to be able to address the problem? So you need to link it back. So this problem and solution is always leaked. I've also seen, situations where you build a problem, and then it actually solves a totally different problem. I mean, you build a solution which solves a totally different problem than what you had set out to do.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): It's actually okay if it's a new, good problem to solve.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): But make sure you are very clear. What is the link between your problem and your solution?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay? And then, yeah, so that's the main thing.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): For the double diamond. Before I move on, any questions about this?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Yeah, so it's basically, you go broad first, you narrow, then you go broad again, and you narrow. When you're going from problem.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): You research, then you narrow and define what is the problem you want to tackle, and then you go broad to ideate potential solutions, then you need to then prioritize what you are actually prototype and build.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, I'll give you an example, right, of a process. So, this problem is, hotels seem to waste a lot of food every day. I think that they have this problem.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, I go and discover more about this problem. So I research, I do desktop research, I do interviews, I… maybe I walk by a hotel and I observe, maybe if I can observe their buffet line and so on. I try to understand who are the people involved, like the restaurant managers, the customers.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): I try to understand, say, for restaurant managers.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): What are the challenges that they have?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And so on. So…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): For this cover, let's say we speak to restaurant managers from 3 hotels, and we learn a lot about the processes of, you know, how they run their restaurant, and the challenges that they face.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And then, when we come to the second part of the triangle, the define, it's like, okay, we talk to them, they give us, like, so many, like, they share so much, then we need to synthesize what is the main findings.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, you know, do summary, you know, what are the 3 main things, or 5 main things that they are telling me about. So, our finding is that we shortlisted the top 3 most common challenges.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And then for hotel buffets, systematically over-prepare, because if you are in a hotel buffet, as a customer, they cannot have the food run out, right? It won't look nice, and then they'll get a bad reputation, people don't want to come back.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Versus if I…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): don't cook as much, or don't prepare as much, I won't have to throw away a lot, but then food runs out. So, I'd rather prepare more food.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So that I don't run out and it looks good in front of our customers. So, the result is that a lot of the edible food, at the end of the day, is all thrown away.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So that's not… not great, right? So the problem is now being defined, so I'm in the middle of that definition is hotel F&B operations, they do need a practical way to reduce the food waste that the restaurant produces from over-preparation. So this is my problem statement. So all of you.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): You should have a very clear problem statement that you can say in one sentence.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Why is the problem? Who faces the problem? So over here, the problem is our food waste, and it's faced by the hotel F&B operations.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): How might we turn a hotel's unavoidable food waste into something of value?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, besides avoiding the waste, because sometimes, even if you reduce, you will still have some.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Can you do anything with the sum, rather than throwing it into the rubbish bin? Is there anything else you can do with what is thrown away? So two questions, two parts of a problem. So these are actually… you can have one problem, or you can have two problem statements relating to that same,
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): interview, or the same situation. It's up to your team.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay, so, for these two problems, most likely… or actually, not necessarily. You may have the same solution that can address two problems, or you can have different solutions that address different problems. You do have to pick, so that you build… you are building one or two prototypes, for this
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, now that you understand the problem and very clear about the problem, you do some ideation.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, ideating, ideas. So, now you're at the brainstorming stage, so you can brainstorm, like, maybe 10 ways of reducing food waste, whether it's reducing at the source, or composting what is inevitably created.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And then you need to prioritize, right? So you think about the implementation, how would you do that, what's the timeline, the feasibility of, like, okay, stakeholders involved.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): who I have to involve, and can I reach them or not?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Do I need to involve the government? Do I need… then it's not so easy, right, to talk to the government, or their timeline will be very long. If you want to do something at home, then maybe very easy, because you are the decision maker. But if you want to do something at somebody else's place, then you need to get approvals, and so on. So, think about those things.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And scalability. Is this something that you can automate? So, of course, for a prototype, if you can automate it, very good. You don't have to, it can be just a concept that it will be automated.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): what would be the manpower that's needed to implement? What is the budget to build this thing? Maybe you think about, wow, some, nuclear power plant, you know, that's going to cost, like, billions of dollars.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Is that realistic for us? Probably not. But, you know, so think about what would be the budget, that is something that is doable. So, of course, we have the $200 budget, but you can… that's only for prototype, but you need to have an idea of, like, okay, if you were to build this a little bit more, what would be the amount that you would need? So, for this example.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): we can say that we landed on two possible prototypes. So, number one is the Smart BIN to capture data on buffet leftovers, which, if you remember, is very, very similar to what Lumitix
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): the startup that I shared earlier on built. The other idea can be a composting network for restaurants and landscapers. So restaurants can pass the food waste to somebody who does the composting.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And those compost is passed to people who do the gardening, or they have plants, or maybe NEA who have parks, to use the compost.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So that's the two ideas that they… we prioritize. So when you are building a prototype, you can build one, or you can build two, that's fine. Okay, so…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Now it's your turn, because I have been talking a lot, and I see that a lot of you are already, you know, in your team, so if you are not paying attention, you must pay attention now, because this is your time to do the work.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay? So, firstly, you are gonna spend 10 minutes on your own. I will put you into the Teams, in your breakout room, but inside your breakout room for 10 minutes.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): On your own, think and research 3 raised problems you have seen before.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): around you, at home, in your canteen, maybe a parent's company, anything, right? Or your CCA, any school, external thing you've seen before. And 3 base problems that are new to you, like, you don't know about it. So, like,
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Anything, could be anything you can use.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): computer, you can use your internet to search up, these new things. You can use some things that are… you can ask for things that are maybe on the industrial level or commercial level, so that you can also find some answers for things… problems that exist outside of what you are familiar with.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So take 10 minutes to do that.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And you should also try and find out how big that problem is. So even for the problems that you face, if you've seen yourself, do a bit of research to get some idea of the size of the problem. Who else would be involved?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Why is it currently like this?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay? Then, after the first 10 minutes, the next 10 minutes, discuss these problems within your team.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay, that's not the next 10 minutes.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Then, the last 10 minutes, discuss the problem direction. So, you know, if you have a team of a few people, you'll probably be coming up with, like, 10, 15 problems. You cannot do all of them, right? So, from hearing each other's ideas on the problems.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Choose a few, 1, 2, 3, you know, problems, or direction that you, after today, you will go back and conduct further research.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): To make sure you fully understand the problem, because we were talking about, you know, discovery and defining, and then you define your problem statement. And then you can also start brainstorming and prioritizing ideas.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So I know some of you already have a little bit more idea as to what you want to build, so you can discuss already what are the ideas.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay, so that's 30 minutes.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Before we go into the breakout rooms,
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Some of you have signed up on your own and indicated that you are interested to form teams. So, later on, when we open the breakout room, you may not be in a breakout room immediately. What we're gonna do is we'll put you into breakout rooms with
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Other people have signed up solo and also interested to form teams. So when you're in the groups, you can still do your own research for 10 minutes.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Then, share your problem ideas that you have found, with each other.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): To see if…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): you have any, maybe, common ideas or common interests that you can… you want to form a team together. There's no obligation if you want to stay in, solo, that's totally fine. We are okay for you to work on this in a team of one to team of six. So that's… this is for those of you who have signed up on your own.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay, then, we're gonna open the breakout rooms now.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Oh, we are having some technical problems.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): we have some technical problems, we have… the breakout rooms that we had created just now are gone, so what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna create,
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): I'm going to create, rooms now, so I need you guys to give me, like, 2 minutes,
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): To do that. So, in the meantime, you can go, like, quick toilet break, or, like, reply your messages. Give me 2 minutes, alright?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay, I have opened the rooms. I would like you guys, to help me by finding the room with your team name, for those of you in the team, to join, and then go into that room.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Do you guys see…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): the breakout rooms? So, for those of you who have trouble, I can also assign you into the rooms manually.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay, so 10 minutes, the 30 minutes will start now, so, you can take some time to do 10 minutes to do the… your own research, then 10 minutes to discuss, and then the last 10 minutes to narrow down,
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): the direction. I will put the reminders in the broadcast on the timing later on.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Let me see…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Well, hi Ellen! I think you have a question around what, to do in the breakout room.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, we'll be spending,
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): 30 minutes on thinking and researching about waste problems, and then after that, we'll get the students to share what are the ideas that they have in terms of what problems to tackle. So we started at 4.30, it's been about 10 minutes, so we have another 20 minutes.
kai yuan (NA): That's title.
Tris: I have a face in my thumbs.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): I'm sick.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): It's been 30 minutes, hopefully you guys have managed to think about what direction you want to go in. I'm gonna start closing the breakout rooms so everybody who are currently inside will start coming out, so I'm gonna start closing the rooms.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And they will have, 60 seconds to come back, so we'll all be back in 60 seconds.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Oh my god.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And we'll continue.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Speak.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Hi, everyone!
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Hope you guys had good conversations with your teammates. For those of you who just came out from your breakout rooms.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): We made…
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Bingo!
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Hello?
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): No.
Alan: Yas tires, ai?
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): What grade is…
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Feed me.
escher (team ecoforge): What?
Alan: Oh, you're there,
escher (team ecoforge): You're lagging.
escher (team ecoforge): Hold on.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): We don't.
Xinyi_EcoGems: I'm so sorry, but I think you're muted, we cannot hear you.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Oh my gosh, thank you so much, Cindy! Okay, yes, so sorry, no wonder nobody was replying to me. Okay, thanks, for letting me know that I was muted this whole time. So, welcome back, everybody, from the pickup rooms. Hopefully, you guys had good conversations with your teammates, and have an idea of what problems you guys are solving for.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): What I have for you is actually bonus industry partner challenge statements.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And this means that you can choose some of this step, you can choose these challenge statements.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): To build your prototype for. And if you do so, we will actually share your idea with the partner, and if actually possible, they might choose to prototype it or pilot your solution
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Where they are facing that problem. So that's a bonus, and it's also not guaranteed that if you choose to build something for them, they will definitely use it, but that is an opportunity, that is possible. So you have to be, you know, of course, very convincing with your proposed solution for them to take it up. So what I'm going to do is I'm going to share high level.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): right now, what are the challenge statements that the partners have given you? And afterwards, on email, I will actually give you more detailed, information about what else they are looking for, what might be some of the constraints or considerations they have, like maybe budget, etc.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, firstly, we have SUSS, the university, who have set 3 challenge statements with us.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Firstly, is improving food waste segregation. So how might SULSS improve their food waste segregation at selected campus outlets
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): to reduce contamination and increase the amount of food waste that can be effectively composted. So they do have a composting, kind of, equipment on their campus.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): But how do they, kind of, effectively do the segregation? Because not all food waste can be segregated. Maybe sometimes the big chicken bones can't be composted, and so on. So how do, how would you put something to solve that? Chair statement number two.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Enhancing compost utilization. How might SUSS develop sustainable and scalable ways to use or distribute the compost generated on campus, so that it benefits both the SUSS and wider community? So this is more like a… like a distribution challenge statement.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): That's just more a distribution channel statement. So once you have the output, which is the compost, you know, they use it, all the SUSS, gardens, everything, but maybe that's too much. So what can… who can we pass this excess compost to?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Then, term statement 3 is reduction of waste generated by customers.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): How might SUSS encourage the diners at the selected food outlets, reduce food waste? So maybe order, don't over-order or finish what they have already ordered. So that's the three trend statements from SUSS. Next, we have a chance statement from Vida City. So…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): They run a few event spaces. Our events generate food and packaging waste almost daily from deliveries, diningware, excess food.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Decision makers are often their partners and co-organisers. They like to explore ways to encourage or incentivize partners to adopt reusables, and participants to accept reusables, or a bring your own culture at community events. So how might you build a solution to address this problem?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And the third, challenge statement we have is from Kids Tropic, which is an indoor children's playground. So the challenge statement is, how might we design an engaging, play-based learning journey that helps preschool children aged 4 to 6 understand plastic waste and practice simple, sustainable habits in their everyday lives?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, after this, over email, I will be sharing
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Details about these challenge statements, which is including maybe what will be their implementation considerations, whether they'll be happy to host you if your solution is selected, or not.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Alright, so if you are interested, you have to tell me that you want to tackle this challenge statement so that, you know, we can coordinate with the internship partner for the next steps.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Alright, optional. Totally optional. You can build a solution for a different problem. You do not have to choose from these, five challenge statements over here.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Cliff?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Hopefully that's clear.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay, so we will share more details over email. Any questions, reach out anytime. So instead of a break, we are going to continue, hopefully it's okay, on the last bit on discovery and defining the problem. Skipping this…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): once again, you know, back to… because I know you guys maybe did some desktop research, just now during the 10 minutes. That's very…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): basic, right? That's very first step, but you need to go back and do a little bit more research about the problem to make sure you understand the context of the entire problem, because you think that this problem is faced by this person, but who else is involved? What else is involved? There's probably no problem that is very, very simple.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And if it is, then maybe it's already solved, right? So if it's a problem that still exists, there are probably reasons why it hasn't been solved, and it's probably because, actually, the problem is a lot more complex than you think. There are more people that need to be involved, or people who need to change their mindset, so you need to
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Go back and do more, research and, kind of interviews or surveys.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, we're gonna go through this kind of three-step process of
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): discovery and defining the problem. So, first thing is to explore, right?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And why do you need to do these three steps? It's really to avoid making the wrong assumptions, make sure you're tackling the right problem, and also make sure that you are building the right foundations to build the right solution.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay? So, I'm sure in your schools, your exams, your teacher always tell you when you're doing your exams.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Read the question carefully.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): I think all of you must have heard this many, many times when you're teachers, because… why? So that when you're answering the question, you're actually answering the right question. It's the same thing here.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): You need to make sure that whatever you are built, before you decide what to build, right, you need to know what is the problem you are solving for. So, make sure you have a very, very clear understanding of the problem.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, exploring.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): You should be kind of mapping out everyone that's related to the waste. Is it the individual? Is it the shops? Is it the recycling partner? Is it the government?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Is it the regulations?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): etc. So, mapping out everyone who is related to the creation of the waste.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): You also should research on what are the solutions that already exist.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): You don't really want to build something that somebody has already done, it's already fully scaled, and then you are building the same thing, and you are later, you are smaller, doesn't really make a lot of sense. So make sure you already know what's out there when you are building. Make sure you can say why your solution is different from other people's solution.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay? And then… A journey map of, like, when
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): is the waste created? Is it created, when it's bought, and it's not used, or it's created, before, when they are producing a product, and before it's ready, there's a lot of waste that's created. So, kind of pinpoint when the waste is created. Or is it like, oh, the thing can only be used one time, and after that, it's immediately a waste? Or is it a thing, say, can use
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): 10 times, and afterwards, it's obsolete, and it has to be… it has to find a different, way to use the waste.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, next is looking, so observing. So, what are the activities, environments, interactions, objects, and users?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): involved in this problem, research on the waste data. So, you need to have a clear baseline before you know, you know, if your solution will make any impact on reducing the waste. So, how much waste is being created from this problem right now?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Where is it from? How often is it, created? Is it on a weekly basis? There will be, like, 10 tons of waste that the restaurant throws away, you know, etc. So you need to be very clear on numbers as well.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay, then the final thing is asking.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): this is where a lot of people will, you know, outsource it to AI, and just, like, you tell me research all about this, and then I take your… whatever the AI tell me as the gospel truth, you know. But that's not enough. Most of the time, you actually need to talk to the real people who face the problems.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): To be able to know for sure that what you understand about a problem is actually correct, because
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): there's just a lot of, maybe, details that can be lost if you don't talk to the people who really face a problem. It's like… it's like if, you know, your… maybe your teacher or your parent assumes you have certain problems.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): But actually, they didn't tell you about… you didn't… you didn't have a conversation about it, they just assumed.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Do you think that they really know your problems?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): maybe not, right? It's only when you have a conversation, they actually ask you what is the problem, and you tell them what is the problem, or they give you a safe space to share about your real problems, then they will know, then they will understand. So it's the same thing, you know, if you don't…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): have a kind of an open conversation with your users, or target users, how will you know the problems they really face? So…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): when… you don't have to, like, write this down, but these are just questions for you to, to guide your discovery process. So this is called Empathy Map. So you should be, you know, you put a user in the center of the map, and then you are mapping out.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): What are they thinking and feeling? What are they seeing?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Which is, like, the environment around them, what other people are doing, maybe they are very affected by the trends, maybe they will be, you know, if there's a trend to do recycling and it's a trendy thing to do, then they will do recycling. Or what are they saying and doing? So, they can say that I always recycle, but do they actually do it? So.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): there's a difference between all these things, and then what do they hear? What… what… whether it is, you know, are they, do they take their news from social media? With social media, is it… are they always on TikTok? Are they always on Instagram? What are the type of news that they are hearing, through the channels that they consume?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And importantly, so that does this, like, kind of a basic first level of, like, understanding your user. Then, importantly, you need to understand what pains they have, and what gains they need.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): when you are mapping out the pain and the gain, you do need to make sure that the… because this is the first step, right, which is to understand your problem. When you go to the second step, which is building your solution, you need to think back, does my solution actually address a pain that they have? Does it address a gain that they want?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay, so I now have this, question for you guys.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Which is…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): when there is… so you want to solve a problem, and the user also has a problem. Do you think that these things are the same?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Yes, no, maybe. So who thinks it's yes?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Who thinks that the problem that you want to solve and the problem of the user is the same.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay, nobody.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Who thinks it's a no?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay, some people say it's not a prop- it's not the same. Who says maybe, or it depends?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay, some people say yes. Okay, so, actually.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): When you think about a problem you want to solve.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): You know, as someone who's in a sustainable hackathon, next time if you become a, you know, an entrepreneur who's tackling, who's building, like, sustainability-related problems, yeah, what are you thinking about? Yeah, thinking about helping the environment, you want to reduce waste, you want to reduce carbon emissions, you want to reduce inefficiencies, you want to create a better future for the future generation.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Right? And other things.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): What are the problems of the user?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Usually, the users are thinking about, okay, what is the manpower required to implement this? Do I have the money? I need to manage my customers, I have inefficiencies, I need something that's convenient. Okay, if I use this solution, I need to integrate it with my 10 other solutions that I'm already using. I need to build my branding so that my customers will continue coming to me. I need to think about regulations and more.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, actually, most likely, they have a bit different thinking to you.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So what do you need to do, right? Actually, understand if this is something that is a harsh truth.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): for people in sustainability, you know, you and I, we're all here because we care about the environment. But the reality is.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Sustainability is often not the top priority for people and businesses, especially when you talk about SMEs in Singapore, you know? They face so much trouble, they have
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Rental is very expensive, manpower is expensive, the cost of their ingredients, everything is rocketing, there are new, competitors coming in. So, is sustainability really the top priority for them? Most of the time, it's not.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So what can you do, right, to make sure that what you are building also speaks to these people, who maybe they will help if it's easy, maybe they will help if it's not going to take away too much attention from every other problem they have, is to actually tailor your pitch to the language that they care about.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, you care about reducing waste, but what do they care about? So, I give you an example, right? Over here, I have an example. So, instead of telling them, I have this solution that will reduce waste.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): I will reduce 10KG of the food waste that you're throwing away every day.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Instead, you can frame it in the, kind of context that matters to them, by telling them.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): My solution can help you reduce how much money you are wasting. Because every day you throw away this 100K of ingredients, it's costing you, like, maybe $500. With my solution, you don't have to throw them away, you save $500 every day.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Now they will listen to you, correct? Because, oh, okay, I care about saving money, or I care about bringing more customers. If you use this solution, you can actually tap on the growing market of sustainability-conscious young consumers.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And you will have a 10% increase in revenue.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): That's also something that the businesses might care about.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, it's also important… the third tip is not every user will have the same problem. So you can say, okay, your customer is restaurants.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): But McDonald's, and maybe a small cafe, and maybe somebody that sells coffee, sort of similar, you know, restaurants, or Chinese restaurants, that are in the mall versus Chinese restaurants, at your neighborhood area. They are own restaurants, but they don't necessarily face the same problem.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, you speak to one person, maybe that gives you a bit of confidence that you are tackling a right problem, but if you speak to more people, then you get more confidence that you are… you are targeting the right problem.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Alright.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay, so…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): That's why it's important to really understand your user, think from their perspective. It's this age HO saying of, like, you know, stepping into somebody else's shoes. That's what this is about.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So I'm gonna do a… show you a short video, it's about 6 minutes, on, how you can ask the right questions to your users.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Hopefully that's.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Interviews are…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Let me go to the first screen.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay, let me know if you can't hear us.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): It should be fine.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Hard.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): But until we can learn to read people's thoughts directly from their brains, they are the single best way to learn about your customers' mindsets, values, and belief systems. Here are 5 common mistakes to avoid. Mistake number one, not building enough rapport.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): While interviews are a great way to learn a lot about your customers, we can't just cold call someone and ask.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Hello? Hey, this is Therese, can you tell me about your mindsets, values, and belief systems?
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): You have to build rapport first. This means introducing yourself, and even making a little bit of small talk. While small talk can sound absolutely dreadful to some people, I think small talk actually gets a bad rap. It can be an incredible rapport-building detective tool.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Hi, Rachel, nice to meet you! Hey! So, I'm Therese, I'm the researcher that will be working with you, and I work with NG, so thanks so much for taking the time to meet with us. Where are you calling in from, by the way? Oh, well, normally I'd be in Milwaukee, but today I am in Chicago.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): If the interviewer hadn't asked where they were calling from, they would never have known that the person was working from somewhere unusual, or that they were helping their family move. Those two pieces of information can say a lot about what someone might care about.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): It's easy to go too far with rapport, though.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): You mentioned you took a lift here, so are you from the area, or… Yeah, I live in Seattle. Oh my gosh, I used to live in Kirkland! Really? Yeah! So, oh, Seattle's so cool, isn't it? Yeah. I guess Kirkland's kind of changed a lot, I know, over the last 5 years. Like, I'm originally from Jersey City, and like, over there, it's like, every 5 years there's a new building, and yeah, Kirkland, I guess it's a little more stable, but, you know, Seattle is pretty cool. Yeah.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): This conversation got derailed really fast, because the interviewer made it about her own lived experiences, rather than that of the interviewee. It's easy to do that when you're trying to be seen as likable, or approachable as a person.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): But don't worry so much about being liked, and focus on being an active listener instead. Mistake number two, not probing enough.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Probing questions are questions that help gain specific, in-depth, follow-up information about a topic.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): A lot of interviewers will shy away from probing too much, either because it feels rude to pry, or because it makes them look like they don't know much about the field.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Yeah, the OKRs are a really high priority on the stakeholders list right now, so we've been working with PMs to get the backlog on the APIs all straightened out.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): However, playing dumb is often a good tactic to get more information that otherwise wouldn't have been offered up freely.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Even if you have a good speculation for what some words or phrases may mean, sometimes assumptions are incorrect, so it's worth asking anyway.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): When you say PMs, that means… totally the project manager. Oh, actually, the product manager. Yeah, we use PJM for the project manager, but not everyone uses the right acronym.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Can you tell me more about that? Oh, yeah, the wrong people reply to emails all the time. It's really annoying.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): See? Probing can shed light on problems that you may not have known existed.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Mistake number 3.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Multitasking during the interview.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): I get it. The texts, the pings, the calendar reminders… we don't love when these disrupt an interview, and some of it is unavoidable, even when we mute our devices. But the biggest culprit of multitasking during interviews? Note-taking.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Not only are we terrible note-takers when we're facilitating an interview, but it also makes us poor facilitators by taking our eye contact away from the participant. Instead.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Delegate note-taking to someone else, and when possible, record your interviews for transcription and analysis later.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Mistake number 4. Allowing observers to influence the interview.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): An interview is a one-on-one conversation. And when people are interested in observing research, that can be a good thing. While it's not a deal-breaker to have an observer or two, imagine five people staring at you as you respond. It gets a little scary. And if more than one tries to interject at the same time.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Yikes. If you record the interview, that can help avoid some of the issues with too many observers. But nonetheless, you should share some clear ground rules, like limiting the number of staff in the room to 3 people max.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And have only the facilitator ask questions. After all, it's the facilitator who's built the rapport. Last but not least, the most compromising of all mistakes. Number 5.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Leading the participant. Sometimes, researchers accidentally show their cards and say a little too much. Or they phrase a question a certain way, which primes the participant to respond differently, their answers skewed by researcher behavior. For example, if I were to ask.
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): How do mobile devices play a role during in-store price comparisons? This might prime the participant to give me examples of times they've used their mobile devices to compare prices. But if I were to ask, how do you shop for appliances?
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): We might find very different user behavior, like foregoing mobile devices, or maybe even uncovering new behavior, like researching brand reputations in advance. So…
Audio shared by Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Keep the study's purpose relatively vague, keep questions as open-ended as possible, and mind your body language as you go. So there you have it! If you're interested in more user interview tactics, check out our full-day course on user interviews at nnroup.com.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): All right, okay, so hopefully that was helpful. This will be linked in the, slides if any of you wanted to, kind of, review that video. And then next, I'm going to… go into our last, kind of.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): the second diamond. So, ideas and prioritization. So, just now I mentioned a reminder that, when you are understanding your user, you need to map out the pain and the gain and make sure that your solution addresses this.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So what else?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): when you are creating your ideas, so this is something that we will actually go into more at the hackathon, but because I know some of you are, you know, eager to get started, and you should be starting to think about ideas for the problems that you are tackling.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): The tips would be don't limit yourself from the start, be bold and creative.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And very importantly, you know, remember this, you can create more impact if more people each do a bit than if only very few people do a lot. So I'll give you an example, right? When we talk about, you know, eating less meat and becoming vegetarian.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): rather than forcing people to be fully vegan, like, everybody must be fully vegan, then, like, very few people can really commit to not eating meat at all. Rather than that, you know, we created things like a meatless Monday, so everybody don't eat meat on Monday, or we avoid eating meat, at least one day a week.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Right? So that helps. So all of those things
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So everybody, if you know everybody in the world cuts our eating of meat by 1%, that's 1 whole percent. But if only, like, 10 people in the world are fully vegan, then that's very, very little impact. So that's what it means. So if your solution is easier to deploy at skill.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): That will definitely create more impact.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Make it easy for the user. So, when you are creating your idea, you put, once again, put yourself in the shoes of the user.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): help them think about if they were using your solution, what would be some adoption friction? So, adoption frictions would be like, oh, do they need to switch?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, say just now, Jonathan, when he was sharing about meals, okay, instead of using your tapa box, which is, you know, straight away after eating, you just throw away, now you have a reusable. You know, that's the problem of washing and cleaning, you need to bring an extra container with you everywhere. So what…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): can you do to change those frictions, right? So, for example, a company like Muse, they take away that washing and logistics, you know, they just return it back at your office.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): You don't have to do anything else. Everything else is taken care of by the solution.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And how would you mitigate, those frictions? And the last tip is on how would you measure impact?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Soul… When you have a solution.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And you are trying to convince more people to join you.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): you will want to know… want to be very clear. If you use my solution, what is the impact for you? It can be on waste diversion, it can also be on, like, carbon emissions reduced, it can be on how much money you save, and so on. So, put some numbers to what your solution can do.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Alright.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And… Now…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): If you recall, at the start, I shared about 4 deliverables with you guys, so now I want to kind of zoom in on what… the second deliverable, which is the scale-up plan. So what is the scale-up plan?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, this is actually a slide deck that you need to submit before the showcase, so you need to submit it latest by 1 October in PDF format, so it can be your slides.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And optionally, you can use some of the slides that I created as a supplementary asset for Showcase. That means, you know, alongside your prototype, you can have on your laptop screen, kind of some of the slides that you think would be interesting to share with the public who are coming to see, and learn about what cool things you guys have built.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, for what to include in the SCAR plan.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, I have put in, like, all point bullet points.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): you can think about, like, maybe one slide per section, or one to two slides per section, right? So the first thing is a problem.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So you should… in your slides, you should be addressing what problem are you solving, size of a problem, who's the target user, who else is involved, why you picked this problem.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay? And then in the, other parts under the problem, you can think about what do you learn about the problem through this entire process? What do you still want to learn about this problem? Because it may uncover some gaps in your knowledge as you are building this.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And then you need to share about the prototype that you have built and tested, so you describe what it would be in the real world, you know, like, if you really deploy it, how it looks like. And of course, then, that's the kind of the dream, and then you describe your prototype on, you know, what you've actually built, to represent the big dream.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): How you tested it, where you tested it, who you tested it with.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): The findings and the insights from the building and the testing process, as well as the impact. So how much waste you actually diverted using your prototype.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And then we talk about reflections. So what do you learn about this journey? It could be relating to sustainability or innovation, or the specific problem you've chosen to tackle. What was the biggest challenge that you had, and how did your team handle it?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): What were the skills that your team built, developed, or improved?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And then, last part on scaling up, which is, if you were to continue this project.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So we want you to bring a bit of, like, long-term mindset into this.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So that, you can think about, you know, if you were to really build, more long-term solutions, what are the considerations you need to have?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, you should include your execution plan, your timeline for the next 6 months, stakeholders that will be involved, and how you would bring them in, and a budget breakdown for what you would need for the next 6 months.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And if we like your idea, as well as you are committed to continuing, we can… there's a potential committed teams to get post-program support for further development and deployment.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So if we can find you, like, an industry partner that's, you know, facing the problem that you are trying… that you are solving for, and you have a solution, we can actually, help you get that industry in road to pilot those solutions.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Of course, this is only for very, very committed teams with a very good plan, okay? So, along the way, please let me know any questions you have, in terms of getting there.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Then, final tips!
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): in terms of this kind of slide deck on the scale-up plan is to include as much photos as you can. So, it can be photos of that
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): design, the building and the testing process, so you can take photos of your prototype, maybe even, like, your first version, your prototype, your sketch, your team members working on this, you can take photos with your mentors.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): for those when you are doing interviews, if you're going on site visits, etc. So those are quite helpful for, allowing people to visualize your journey. So you can… if you have, you know, illustrations.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): to showcase the demo that you are building, etc, or the mock-up, those are helpful. Include acknowledgements that you have, like, who helped you with your project.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And I do want to highlight a little bit on the use of AI, because, I… in my daily job, I do see a lot of slides that are created by AI.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): I… we will definitely have… so it's not just myself, right? It's also because of the jury panel that will be there to assess you on the day itself. There is a strong bias against obvious AI output. It's okay to use AI, especially as a first cut.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): But it should not replace actual user interactions, and you should now definitely be able to explain why you are submitting. So if I ask you, like, follow-up questions or specific things, you should be able to answer.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And you should be owning all the words and all the images that are on the slide. Is this representative of your team? Is it representative of what you want to build? Is it good enough that other people, once they look at it, they're like, oh, I actually want to support this team to continue building this further?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Right, put yourself once again in the shoes of the people who will be looking at your materials.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So,
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): As a quick wrap-up of today's kickoff, we covered quite a few topics, right? We covered Singapore's waste problems with the Kahoot, we talked about the NIRs, we talked about the Double Diamond Framework, gave you some examples.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So… In preparation for the hackathon day one, on the 5th of September.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): You should come with this very, very clearly in your teams, right, or on your own for the solo, members.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): a clear problem statement. What problem are you solving? How big is the problem? Who's the target user? Who else is involved? And why do you pick this problem? So, if you recall, right, if you… if I go back to my skill plant test, already the first two
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Pots.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Of course, you don't have to put it into slides, but you need to have it clearly in your head, or within your team alignment, what is the problem you are tackling, okay? And then the other
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): thing you need to prepare is two to three prioritized ideas. So, you can think of many ideas in your team, but you need to prioritize with two to three that you want to further develop at the hackathon. So, you need to describe your concept and what it would be like as a real-world solution, how it would work.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay, so once again, going back to the scale plan, there's actually this part already, this first thing.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So you don't have to do double work. So you first, you can start preparing all of these things.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay, then I have some recommended videos and articles for you to learn more about waste and recycling in Singapore that you can watch after this, if you would like to get a bit more understanding about waste challenges. I would really recommend these, kind of videos, for you to learn a little bit more.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): We are coming towards the end of our kickoff. Thank you, everybody, for kind of your attention and staying on until now, but before you go, I have some very important, reminders. The most, most important thing is we have a venue change for the Hackathon Day 1.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So because we have so many of you who have signed up, we are so happy to see all of you. Our first venue is a bit too small, so we've had to find another option for all of us to be able to fit in the room, and we've managed to partner up with Lorong AI at Wan North.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So we are so, so thankful for the Vida City and Lorong AI team, because they've managed to, you know, sponsor the venue for this program, and we will all be meeting at one-off.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, 1 North is slightly to the west, it's west side of Singapore, so make sure you check out the address, and make sure you are going to the right place,
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): on the 5th of September, Saturday.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): The session will be from 9am to 1pm.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And the reporting time is 8.45am.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, 8.45am, I hope to see all of you there. There are a few things to bring. You should bring a water bottle, there's a water dispenser at the venue. You should bring your stationery and some paper, and if you have a laptop, I would suggest you to bring them.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): If you do not, it's okay, we can walk around that. And then… yeah.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): If you have any questions, anyway… Dress code!
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): To be honest, I would say…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Casual is also fine. Don't… just be a little bit more presentable. I would say t-shirts, and if you have berms, that's fine. That's… that's okay. You don't have to wear school uniforms, if you… Yeah, yeah, basically, you don't have to wear school uniforms, just wear something that's comfortable.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay? So nothing, like, too revealing or inappropriate, just something that's, that you are comfortable with, okay?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And then, for those of you… Okay, before we go off, I have a question from one of you earlier.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): That I need to… that I want to share with you guys. So the question I had was around the trash diary.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, will lunch be provided? Lunch will not be provided. We will be, preparing some light bites for you to eat along the way, but because we end at 1pm, so hopefully you are able to go for your lunch after 1PM.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, lunch is not provided, okay? To be very, very clear, lunch is not provided. We will have some, light bites, for you guys.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, back to the question on trash diary that one of you had.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): I'll give you an example of what it would be like. So let's say, you know, in your… the very simple example, if in your home, you have your plastic bottles, you have maybe your,
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay, so let's go with plastic bottles first. So, if you're collecting these plastic packaging or containers with your family, you bag them up.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): tie them up, you put on a weighing scale, and take a picture of what the weighing scale says, so maybe it's, like, 500 grams, or 1KG, or 2KG. That is one photo evidence for that amount.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): It can be also, like, food waste. So let's say, you know, your family bought a lot of oranges, and then you order peel, that is… you would, like, take out the peel, and you would throw it away. If, you… instead of throwing it away, you are actually sending it to a partner to do composting, or if you are doing composting at home.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Take a picture of that, and then record that as the waste that you are diverting.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Those are, like, household examples. You can also do the same thing or similar thing, say, in your school. So maybe you can talk to your school, or your lecturer, or within your classroom, right? You say, okay, I want to put a BIN here, then I want all my classmates to help me contribute, and throw their plastic bottles here.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Before you bring it to the recycling center, right, make sure they are all rinsed out, okay? So that it can actually be recycled, because if your bottles are dirty, then actually it just gets, sent to the incinerator anyway.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, once a week can collect, you know, all the trash that your classmates have helped you collect, weigh it, record it, okay? You need to take the pictures. Then, there's a canteen example, like, school,
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): kind of school setting. Maybe some of you, you happen to know of a restaurant, or a…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): maybe food manufacturing facility. Then, every day they make tofu, or they make something, and they throw away a lot of the, kind of, the, waste food. Currently, they throw away. If you can come in with a solution to help them, okay, it's still you don't throw away, I help you do this, and I redirect this waste to somebody else who can use it.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): That is also okay.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So I do have quite a few questions in the chat. Let me go through the questions one by one, okay?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): documents provided, so you can see suggested formats of the deliverables. So…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): I will send an email over after this with the, like, the templates that you need to fill out, the materials from today. Then, if there are still questions around the format or the deliverables, just ping me, and then I can, get back to you directly. And then another question is, can we recycle using a Tencent return machine?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Absolutely. But you need to take a picture of how much you are recycling. We are basing it on weight, so kg. So before you put it into the machine, you just need to weigh how much you have.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Collected.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And then, Wan Ching has a question.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay, so, very good question. If the prototype is a Wizard of Oz type, hence not a working prototype that can be actually implemented, right, it's just, like, manual or something, how is it possible to measure the waste diverted?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Reminder that the waste diversion does not need to be related to your product.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So your protagon can do one thing.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And you can find other ways to actually divert the waste.
Alan: distribution.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Alright then, Alan, you have a question?
Alan: Yeah, just on the subject on this, the trash daily… the daily trash, right?
Alan: Hello? Can you hear me?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): No, yes, yes.
Alan: Okay, the daily trash you're talking about, right? Do you need to be…
Alan: So-called the result of your invention.
Alan: Because, you see, you have to be related to what you're doing, right?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): No. So, actually, let me see, let me go back to the front part.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So the two, kind of, prizes… on…
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): on, best… biggest impact and best innovation. So over here is stated clearly, right, that the impact of what you are diverting, it need not be directly attributed to your project.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So you can build a solution for something, but you can have a different idea, or a different way to collect the waste. And that's okay.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): That's okay. So today, right now, you don't have an idea of what you're building yet, you can go back and you can tell your parents or your family, stop throwing away all our plastic containers, give it to me, I want to recycle.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): That's totally okay, it has nothing to do with whatever you have built, but you are still making an impact. And that's the thing we want to… for you guys to take away, which is, you don't always need to do something very fancy to create impact. Even you can start today, in small ways.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay? So, does not need to be directly attributed to your prototype.
Alan: No, it's not… it's not about prototype, it's about… this is a competition, so everybody will come up with their own ideas, how to… how to, you know, you know…
Alan: solve the problem of waste, mah. So if you… if you have come up with some kind of, okay, now I'll go to my canteen and throw away and get all the waste and so on, right? Nothing to do with my project, you know?
Alan: So is this what you won?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Yes, so that's why there are two prizes.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So there are two different prices. One is for biggest impact. If, because… the thing is, if today you really go to a canteen and you manage to divert all the waste from the canteen.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): That is impact.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): There is impact.
Alan: Okay, nothing to do with the… nothing to do with the competition,
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Of the competition. So it's still based on the biggest impact. So all of that, you track it.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And if you are the team that diverts the largest amount of base of weight, like number of kg.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): You can win the biggest impact price.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): It says time to pick out a garbage truck. You need to become a… you need to pick out the recyclables from the garbage truck,
Alan: Oh, okay. And then, is there a start date and an end date? That means my product or my design concept has not finalized. By the time I finalize my design concept.
Alan: Then, when you start counting whether how much waste I remove every day.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay, so the ways you can collect… count it from today until 1st of October.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So just before the showcase ends.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So, all of that data… so, you need to… you can start recording from today onwards.
Alan: Okay, thank you.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): And then… let me see, any… There's a question on which recycling center we can go. It can be any recycling center, you can put it to the blue bins at your void decks.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): That's not our first recommendation. Our first recommendation is if you can go to maybe an off-taker. So someone who will actually use your specific, item that you're collecting, that would be great. So, there are some, maybe, startups or community initiatives where they take food waste to compost. If you can find those, that's number one. If you can find people who, maybe they take, your waste plastic, they melt it, they make it into a new product that
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): can be sold, that's also very good. But if you can't find those, putting it to the blue BIN, that is acceptable.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): All right? So, if you have any other questions after this, you can always reach out to me on, WhatsApp or email.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): if there are questions that I think, you know, other people will also have, I will just share it with everybody, in an updated FAQ or through the WhatsApp channel, okay? So, finally, I think that's it that I have for now.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Monsieur?
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Okay, I think that's all for now, for everybody else. So after this, we will be sharing with you the recording, so it will be, by tomorrow morning, you will get the follow-up email, and then,
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): please reach out to me anytime to ask questions. For those of you, if you haven't joined the WhatsApp group, please do so as well. Yeah.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Then… We are officially concluding the kickoff.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): Thank you, everybody, for staying on until now.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): For those of you who are joining solo and interested to form teams, please stay on for another few minutes so I can discuss with you on the next steps.
Jamie (SG Eco Loop): So I'll stop the recording right now as well.